<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>NewsHub</title>
	<atom:link href="/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description></description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 04 Nov 2024 15:36:21 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.6.2</generator>
	<item>
		<title>At least 95 people dead in Spain’s worst floods in three decades</title>
		<link>/at-least-95-people-dead-in-spains-worst-floods-in-three-decades/</link>
					<comments>/at-least-95-people-dead-in-spains-worst-floods-in-three-decades/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[root]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 04 Nov 2024 15:36:18 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=38</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Soldiers aid search for dozens still missing as prime minister warns extreme weather may not be over At least 95 people have died in eastern, central and southern&#160;Spain&#160;after torrential rains triggered the country’s deadliest floods in three decades, unleashing torrents of muddy water that surged through cities, towns and villages, trapping people in their homes,...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Soldiers aid search for dozens still missing as prime minister warns extreme weather may not be over</h3>



<p>At least 95 people have died in eastern, central and southern&nbsp;<a href="https://www.theguardian.com/world/spain">Spain</a>&nbsp;after torrential rains triggered the country’s deadliest floods in three decades, unleashing torrents of muddy water that surged through cities, towns and villages, trapping people in their homes, bringing down trees, and cutting off roads and railway lines.</p>



<p>As the search for dozens of missing people continued, motorists were urged to stay off the roads and away from swollen rivers amid warnings that the severe weather was not over and that the number of deaths could still rise.</p>



<p>By Wednesday afternoon, the Valencian government’s emergency coordination centre said the latest number of known deaths in the region was 92, while the central government delegation in the neighbouring Castilla-La Mancha region reported two deaths, including that of an 88-year-old woman in the city of Cuenca. Another death was reported in Andalucía’s Málaga province.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image" id="3d61f782-370e-4f26-88c0-cfa441874b83"><a href="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2024/oct/30/spain-floods-torrential-rain-deaths#img-1"><img decoding="async" src="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/6a1f00b09aa4ba66aa3468aa46364f685f5e3d38/0_250_3708_2225/master/3708.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" alt="Members of emergency services rescue people trapped in their homes after floods in Letur, Albacete."/></a><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Members of emergency services rescue people trapped in their homes after floods in Letur, Albacete.&nbsp;Photograph: Víctor Fernández/AP</figcaption></figure>



<p>The Valencian authorities urged people to keep clear of flooded or cut-off roads, saying the emergency services needed access and that more flood water could accumulate. More than 1,000 soldiers from Spain’s emergency response units were deployed to the devastated areas. The central government also sent nine forensic experts to Valencia to help with the task of identifying bodies.</p>



<p>Images on Spanish TV showed turbulent, muddy water coursing through the town of Letur in the eastern province of Albacete on Tuesday, dragging cars through its streets.</p>



<p>“Yesterday was the worst day of my life,” Ricardo Gabaldón, the mayor of Utiel, a town in Valencia, told the national broadcaster RTVE. He said several people were missing in his town. “We were trapped like rats. Cars and rubbish containers were flowing down the streets. The water was rising to 3 metres [10ft],” he said.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image" id="d9940c6d-2c4b-44af-9a34-932349f84312"><a href="https://www.theguardian.com/world/gallery/2024/oct/30/torrential-rain-brings-deadly-flooding-to-spain-in-pictures"><img decoding="async" src="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/89a542e1d9ea291118100b1df64ad7c8f427ea5a/0_372_5851_3511/master/5851.jpg?width=460&amp;quality=85&amp;auto=format&amp;fit=max&amp;s=a2c138163e92f88e1fef30d779edcb09" alt="Residents clean the street next to cars piled up after being swept away by floods in Valencia, Spain."/></a></figure>



<p>One elderly couple were rescued from the upper storey of their house by a military unit using a bulldozer, with three soldiers accompanying them in the huge shovel.</p>



<p>Television reports ran videos from members of the public showing waters flooding into the ground floors of flats, streams overflowing their banks and at least one bridge giving way.</p>



<p>A high-speed train with nearly 300 people onboard derailed near Málaga, although rail authorities said no one was hurt. The high-speed rail service between Valencia city and Madrid was interrupted, as were several commuter lines.</p>



<p>Tuesday’s floods were Spain’s worst since 1996, when 87 people died after torrential rain hit a campsite in the Pyrenees mountains. Europe’s most recent catastrophic floods&nbsp;<a href="https://www.theguardian.com/environment/2021/aug/23/climate-crisis-made-deadly-german-floods-up-to-nine-times-more-likely">came in July 2021, killing 243 people in Germany, Belgium, Romania, Italy and Austria</a>.</p>



<p>The intense rain has been attributed to a phenomenon known as the&nbsp;<em>gota fría</em>, or&nbsp;<a href="https://www.theguardian.com/environment/2024/oct/28/weather-tracker-cold-drop-to-cause-heavy-rain-in-spain">“cold drop”</a>, which occurs when cold air moves over the warm waters of the Mediterranean. This creates atmospheric instability, causing warm, saturated air to rise rapidly, leading to heavy rain and thunderstorms.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image" id="a08c7ab8-9b81-483a-afb3-dde610bf6fce"><img decoding="async" src="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/4f89bb3b44243a9029a5a70d6b943a9ce4b477ef/0_0_1920_1080/1920.jpg?width=465&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" alt="'A living hell': officials search for missing after catastrophic flooding in Spain – video report"/><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">&#8216;A living hell&#8217;: officials search for missing after catastrophic flooding in Spain – video report</figcaption></figure>



<p>Scientists say extreme weather events such as heatwaves and storms are becoming more intense because of the climate crisis. Warmer air can hold more water vapour.</p>



<p>In a televised statement on Wednesday morning, Spain’s prime minister, Pedro Sánchez, called for unity, solidarity and vigilance. “We mustn’t let our guard down because the weather front is still wreaking havoc and we can’t say that this devastating episode is over,” he said</p>



<p>“There are still weather warnings in Andalucía, Valencia, Aragón, Castilla y León, in Catalonia, in Extremadura, in Navarre, in La Rioja and in Ceuta. That’s why I’m asking people in those areas to take special care: to stay off the roads; to avoid travelling close to ravines, riverbanks and riverbeds, and to heed the advice of the emergency services and of the police. No one should be putting their life at risk.”</p>



<p>By 6pm local time, a red weather warning remained in place for the zone around Jerez de la Frontera in southern Andalucía, while orange warnings were still in force in the same region for Cádiz, Seville and the area close to the strait of Gibraltar.https://interactive.guim.co.uk/uploader/embed/2024/10/archive-zip/giv-4559QwA3kNsrLub4/</p>



<p>The prime minister said Spain had experienced more than its fair share of natural and health emergencies in recent years, mentioning the Covid pandemic, Storm Filomena in January 2021, and the volcanic eruptions in the Canary Islands that year. He said such adversity had often brought out the best in the country.</p>



<p>“We’re going to lend a hand and help those who can’t get into their homes or who are looking for relatives or friends or loved ones,” he said. “But most of all, right now, we’re going to stand with those who are suffering the loss of their loved ones.”</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image" id="df08f952-64c8-401d-8dbd-8b27f585b774"><img decoding="async" src="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/9d4c27daa45106ae204bf1d569b73842a9d042bf/0_0_1920_1080/1920.jpg?width=465&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" alt="Spain's prime minister warns people affected by floods to 'stay on guard' – video"/><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Spain&#8217;s prime minister warns people affected by floods to &#8216;stay on guard&#8217; – video</figcaption></figure>



<p>Three days of national mourning were declared and Spain’s congress held a minute’s silence on Wednesday to commemorate the dead.</p>



<p>King Felipe offered his support to the families of the dead and missing, saying he was heartbroken by the news of the flooding and deaths. “I’m sending strength, encouragement and all the necessary support to all those affected,” he said. “We recognise and appreciate all the local and regional authorities and the emergency and security services as they continue with the titanic task they have been carrying out since the very first moment.”</p>



<p>By 10am on Wednesday, the rains in Valencia had subsided. But Spain’s national weather service forecast more storms on Thursday, with the rains moving to the north-east of the Iberian peninsula.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/at-least-95-people-dead-in-spains-worst-floods-in-three-decades/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>America’s fight with inflation has been won – just in time for a bigger battle</title>
		<link>/americas-fight-with-inflation-has-been-won-just-in-time-for-a-bigger-battle/</link>
					<comments>/americas-fight-with-inflation-has-been-won-just-in-time-for-a-bigger-battle/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[root]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 04 Nov 2024 15:34:12 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Finance]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=32</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Phillip Inman The Fed is likely to cut base rates this month – but its decision will come the day after an explosive US election There could be recriminations, protest marches and even social unrest on US city streets when&#160;Federal Reserve&#160;officials meet at their Washington HQ a day after the election of a new president...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h1 class="wp-block-heading"></h1>



<p><a href="https://www.theguardian.com/profile/phillipinman">Phillip Inman</a></p>



<p>The Fed is likely to cut base rates this month – but its decision will come the day after an explosive US election</p>



<p>There could be recriminations, protest marches and even social unrest on US city streets when&nbsp;<a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/federal-reserve">Federal Reserve</a>&nbsp;officials meet at their Washington HQ a day after the election of a new president on 5 November.</p>



<p>The election of Kamala Harris could bring supporters of Donald Trump on to the streets, while a victory for Trump could provoke widespread anger and condemnation among Democrats.</p>



<p>The Fed is supposed to behave as if it lives outside the political bubble, away from the daily jousting in Congress and the White House. An era-defining election will be more difficult to ignore.</p>



<p>Nevertheless, the Fed is expected to please whoever wins by cutting interest rates and signalling several more reductions, after figures showed a two-year battle against inflation had been largely won in the summer.</p>



<p>Markets currently expect Fed boss Jerome Powell to announce a 0.25-percentage-point reduction in interest rates, to a spread between 4.5% and 4.75%, at a press conference on 7 November.</p>



<p>There are doubts among some Fed officials about whether the defeat of inflation has been permanent and lasting. They worry that businesses will jack up prices by more than the Fed’s 2% annual inflation target in response to a tight labour market that has kept wage increases steady even as inflation has fallen.</p>



<p>However, the most recent jobs data showed the unemployment rate rising from 3.4% to 4.1% over the last 18 months, after hitting 4.3% in July.</p>



<p>The closely watched non-farm payroll report on Friday showed the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/2024/nov/01/us-october-jobs-report">US economy had added just 12,000 jobs in October</a>. That was well below expectations for 113,000. There were special factors at play – the impacts of hurricanes Helene and Milton both affected the month, and a strike at Boeing also had an effect. But even so, analysts were aware of these factors when making their forecasts.</p>



<p>The weak data means that a larger 0.5-percentage-point reduction in the cost of borrowing is possible. A bigger cut would be welcomed by most US workers, whose wage increases have yet to reverse a noticeable slide in living standards.</p>



<p>British workers are similarly hard-pressed and looking forward to a rate cut by&nbsp;<a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/bankofenglandgovernor">the Bank of England</a>&nbsp;to ease mortgage and rental costs.</p>



<p>Policymakers at the Bank’s Threadneedle Street HQ also meet on 6 November and, like Fed officials, deliver their verdict on 7 November.</p>



<p>There is a strong chance the Bank will cut interest rates after governor Andrew Bailey&nbsp;<a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/2024/oct/03/sterling-pound-bank-of-england-andrew-bailey-aggressive-interest-rate-cuts-inflation">told the&nbsp;</a><em><a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/2024/oct/03/sterling-pound-bank-of-england-andrew-bailey-aggressive-interest-rate-cuts-inflation">Guardian</a></em>&nbsp;that it could become a “bit more aggressive” in doing so if inflation continued to cool. That was before the latest official figures showed&nbsp;<a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/2024/oct/16/uk-inflation-bank-of-england-interest-rates">UK inflation had fallen to 1.7% in September</a>&nbsp;– below the Bank’s 2% target and the lowest level in three and a half years.</p>



<p>The Bank will have a big advantage over the Fed, and that relates to the political backdrop for its decisions.</p>



<p>While the Fed will be in the dark about the tax and spending policies of the incoming president,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.theguardian.com/uk-news/2024/oct/30/rachel-reeves-bets-on-public-spending-increases-in-budget-winning-over-voters">Labour’s budget last week</a>&nbsp;gives the Bank a good view of the government’s finances five years ahead.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/americas-fight-with-inflation-has-been-won-just-in-time-for-a-bigger-battle/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Schools close in Lahore as pollution hits record level</title>
		<link>/schools-close-in-lahore-as-pollution-hits-record-level/</link>
					<comments>/schools-close-in-lahore-as-pollution-hits-record-level/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[root]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 04 Nov 2024 15:32:42 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=27</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Ruth Comerford BBC News Unprecedented air pollution in the Pakistani city of Lahore has forced authorities to close all primary schools for a week. From Monday, 50% of office workers will also work from home, as part of a &#8220;green lockdown&#8221; plan. Other measures include bans on engine-powered rickshaws and vendors that barbecue without filters....]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Ruth Comerford</p>



<p>BBC News</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image"><img decoding="async" src="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/480/cpsprodpb/0d58/live/77898210-99dc-11ef-82c3-45a801b7330b.jpg.webp" alt="EPA A blue vehicle sprays water into the air in Lahore as intense smog grips the city."/><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Pakistani municipal corporation workers spray water on roads to control the smog situation.</figcaption></figure>



<p>Unprecedented air pollution in the Pakistani city of Lahore has forced authorities to close all primary schools for a week.</p>



<p>From Monday, 50% of office workers will also work from home, as part of a &#8220;green lockdown&#8221; plan. Other measures include bans on engine-powered rickshaws and vendors that barbecue without filters.</p>



<p>&#8220;This smog is very harmful for children, masks should be mandatory in schools,&#8221; Punjab Senior Minister Marriyum Aurangzeb said.</p>



<p>Lahore, Pakistan&#8217;s second-largest city, topped the world list of cities with the most polluted air for a second time on Sunday.</p>



<p>The air quality index, which measures a range of pollutants, exceeded 1,000 on Saturday, well above the benchmark of 300 considered &#8220;dangerous&#8221; by the World Health Organization, according to data from IQAir.</p>



<p>The level of fine particulate matter in the air, the most damaging to health, also soared well into hazardous levels.</p>



<p>Raja Jehangir Anwar, a senior environment official, said the &#8220;biggest headache&#8221; causing the smog was the practice of burning crop waste, known as stubble, across the Indian border.</p>



<p>Aurangzeb said the fumes were “being carried by strong winds into Pakistan”.</p>



<p>&#8220;This cannot be solved without talks with India,&#8221; she said, adding that the provincial government would initiate such discussions through the foreign ministry.</p>



<p>The government is urging people to stay indoors and avoid unnecessary travel.</p>



<p>Vehicles equipped with pumps are spraying water into the air to help control the smog level. Construction work has been halted in certain areas.</p>



<p>The situation will be assessed again next Saturday to establish whether schools should remain shut.</p>



<p>Inhaling toxic air can have catastrophic health consequences, including strokes, heart disease, lung cancer and some respiratory diseases, according to the WHO.</p>



<p>Last month pupils were&nbsp;<a href="https://www.bbc.co.uk/newsround/articles/c2dlx4y301zo">banned from outdoor&nbsp;</a>exercise until January and school hours were adjusted to prevent children from travelling when pollution levels are the highest.</p>



<p>&#8220;As a mother, I am full of anxiety,&#8221; 42-year-old Lilly Mirza told AFP news agency.</p>



<p>&#8220;Last year was not this bad&#8230; Somebody needs to tell us what has happened. Did a pollution bomb explode somewhere?&#8221;</p>



<p>The smog crisis is worse in winter, when cold, denser air traps pollutants closer to the ground.</p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/schools-close-in-lahore-as-pollution-hits-record-level/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>&#8216;A mesmerising mirage&#8217;: How Monet&#8217;s paintings changed the way we see London&#8217;</title>
		<link>/a-mesmerising-mirage-how-monets-paintings-changed-the-way-we-see-london/</link>
					<comments>/a-mesmerising-mirage-how-monets-paintings-changed-the-way-we-see-london/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[root]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 04 Nov 2024 15:20:47 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Arts & Culture]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=20</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[A new exhibition charts how Claude Monet&#8217;s revolutionary, fog-shrouded visions of the Thames would &#8220;irreversibly alter how London saw itself&#8221;. Some artists help us perceive the world more precisely. A rare few go further. They look beyond looking. Theirs is a deeper reality, more felt than seen. Claude Monet is one of those. In three...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h1 class="wp-block-heading"></h1>



<figure class="wp-block-image"><img decoding="async" src="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/images/ic/480xn/p0jz48hm.jpg.webp" alt="Christie’s Images Waterloo Bridge, Overcast by Monet,1903 (Credit: Photo: Anders Sune Berg)"/></figure>



<p><strong>A new exhibition charts how Claude Monet&#8217;s revolutionary, fog-shrouded visions of the Thames would &#8220;irreversibly alter how London saw itself&#8221;.</strong></p>



<p>Some artists help us perceive the world more precisely. A rare few go further. They look beyond looking. Theirs is a deeper reality, more felt than seen. Claude Monet is one of those. In three visits to London between 1899 and 1901, the French Impressionist, then approaching 60 years of age, embarked upon one of the most ambitious series of penetrating paintings ever undertaken by any artist – a project that is now the focus of a groundbreaking exhibition at the Courtauld Institute,&nbsp;<a target="_blank" href="https://courtauld.ac.uk/whats-on/exh-monet-and-london-views-of-the-thames/" rel="noreferrer noopener">Monet and London: Views of the Thames</a>.&nbsp;</p>



<p>From a murky miasma of toxic, soot-laced smog that choked the very breath of the Thames, Monet magicked up nearly 100 paintings – more than he would devote to any other subject in his long career. His evanescent visions, which dissolve the heft of London&#8217;s crowded bridges and imposing palaces into intangible tapestries of vibrating vapour, would shape forever the way the world conceived of the &#8220;unreal city&#8221;,&nbsp;<a target="_blank" href="https://www.poetryfoundation.org/poems/47311/the-waste-land" rel="noreferrer noopener">as TS Eliot would later call it</a>&nbsp;– a place beyond place that sits outside of time, an ethereal elsewhere.</p>



<p><em>What Monet was really compiling weren&#8217;t studies of a city but experiments in optics – a pioneering treatise on the undiscovered properties of light itself</em></p>



<p>Consider the evaporative power of a single instalment of the sprawling series, London, The Houses of Parliament, Shaft of Sunlight in the Fog. Among the best known of Monet&#8217;s views of the Thames, the painting captures the propulsive turrets of the Palace of Westminster, juddering in a flash of late-afternoon sun that teasingly transparentises a curtain of fog that shrouds the neo-Gothic structure.</p>



<p>During the artist&#8217;s second stay in London in 1901, Monet began chronicling the fluctuating temperaments of the Houses of Parliament from a covered terrace of the recently constructed St Thomas&#8217;s Hospital, directly across the river from the palace on the Southbank. A year earlier, the artist had begun translating, from the balcony of his sixth-floor rooms in the Savoy Hotel where the series began in September 1899, the shifting dispositions of dawn light as it alchemised the rigid reach of Waterloo Bridge and Charing Cross Bridge into luminous levitations. The ensuing studies of the Houses of Parliament, caught at different times of the day and in varying densities of smog and mist, demonstrate a further intensification of the artist&#8217;s understanding of the very essence of his subject.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image"><img decoding="async" src="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/images/ic/480xn/p0jyqslp.jpg.webp" alt="Musée d'Orsay, Paris, Photo: Grand Palais RMN (Musée d’Orsay The Houses of Parliament, Shaft of Sunlight in the Fog, 1904, oil on canvas (Credit: Musée d'Orsay, Paris, Photo: Grand Palais RMN (Musée d’Orsay)/Hervé Lewandowski)"/><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">The Houses of Parliament, Shaft of Sunlight in the Fog, 1904, oil on canvas (Credit: Musée d&#8217;Orsay, Paris, Photo: Grand Palais RMN (Musée d’Orsay)/Hervé Lewandowski)</figcaption></figure>



<p>While Monet&#8217;s work is often celebrated for its exquisite portrayal of light, there is a slight, though significant, imprecision in the praise. What distinguishes his paintings from those of Pissarro, Morisot and his other Impressionist peers is their conviction in the annihilating potential of sun-soaked air, which Monet sees as key to comprehending the ephemerality of form. The world is a mesmerising mirage. Through the lens of Monet&#8217;s painting, form – no matter how stony or static, intransigent or inert – is fungible. It fights for survival.</p>



<p>On first seeing a display of Monet&#8217;s London paintings five years later, a US collector and writer attested to the retinal riddle presented by Monet&#8217;s enthralling canvases, which seem to reverse the respective concretions of material substance and refulgent air. The urban infrastructures,&nbsp;<a target="_blank" href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/25503805?origin=crossref&amp;seq=1" rel="noreferrer noopener">Desmond FitzGerald explained</a>: &#8220;are all so misty that at first the beholder gazes with astonishment at what seems to be a half-finished picture; but gradually, as the eye penetrates the fog, objects begin to come out… The illusion is wonderful, and has never been attempted in exactly the same manner before. The Houses of Parliament shine out of the fog with the colour of old-rose or purple.&#8221;</p>



<p>FitzGerald&#8217;s insistence that what Monet had seized was at once &#8220;an illusion&#8221; and something never before articulated by an artist is telling. Introduced into English in the middle of the 14th Century, the word &#8220;illusion&#8221; is related to &#8220;ludicrous&#8221; and initially denoted a jeering act of mocking deception. Is it possible that Monet&#8217;s mesmeric depictions of the Thames differ so markedly from those of earlier artists because they don&#8217;t, in fact, capture his subject as it actually appeared? Are his paintings, in truth, resplendent lies?</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>&#8216;Light was in the air&#8217;</strong></h2>



<p>Monet was the first to confess that in order to make London a suitable subject for him to take on, a fabricating Insta-filter was required. &#8220;Without the fog,&#8221; he remarked, &#8220;London wouldn&#8217;t be a beautiful city. It&#8217;s the fog that gives it its magnificent breadth. Its regular and massive blocks become grandiose within that mysterious cloak.&#8221; The sheer panic that Monet suffered when he pulled back the curtains in his hotel room – to discover the crisp, clean light of a mistless morning – is palpable. &#8220;Upon getting up,&#8221; he confided to his wife in a letter written in March 1900, &#8220;I was terrified to see that there was no fog, not even the hint of mist; I was devastated and already seeing all my canvases ruined.&#8221; His relief when, &#8220;little by little, with the fires lighting up, smoke and mist returned,&#8221; only corroborates the suspicion that London, as a place, was all but incidental to his purposes. What he was really compiling weren&#8217;t studies of a city but experiments in optics – a pioneering treatise on the undiscovered properties of light itself.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image"><img decoding="async" src="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/images/ic/480xn/p0jyqt5r.jpg.webp" alt="Image Courtesy of the Milwaukee Art Museum. Photo: John R Glembin Waterloo Bridge, Sunlight Effect, 1903, oil on canvas, Milwaukee Art Museum (Credit: Image Courtesy of the Milwaukee Art Museum. Photo: John R Glembin)"/><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Waterloo Bridge, Sunlight Effect, 1903, oil on canvas, Milwaukee Art Museum (Credit: Image Courtesy of the Milwaukee Art Museum. Photo: John R Glembin)</figcaption></figure>



<p>It is among the more intriguing, and under-explored, cultural coincidences that Monet&#8217;s audacious series, which provocatively posits light as pulsing parcels deftly described in short brushstrokes, began at the same moment that, in Germany, the theoretical physicist Max Planck was celebrating a breakthrough in his own conception of light as quanta, or packets of energy. Light, it seems, was in the air. By seizing upon the murky medium of virulent vapours spewing from the chimneys of the factories that crammed the banks of the river – Blake&#8217;s &#8220;dark satanic mills&#8221; – Monet painstakingly tested his paradoxical hypothesis that what is most worth seeing is what is least visible: the vibrating veil that invigorates reality.</p>



<p>So acclimatised are our eyes to seeing the Thames through the smudgy lens of Monet&#8217;s scintillating smoggles, it is almost impossible to imagine how the river could be perceived before he made us aware of the weave of fog&#8217;s &#8220;mysterious cloak&#8221;. Writing in the same year that Monet first set up his easel in the Savoy, Oscar Wilde wrestled with the very existence of fog&nbsp;<a href="https://www.wilde-online.info/the-decay-of-lying-page15.html" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">in his essay</a>&nbsp;The Decay of Lying. &#8220;At present, people see fogs, not because there are fogs,&#8221; Wilde mused: &#8220;but because poets and painters have taught them the mysterious loveliness of such effects. There may have been fogs for centuries in London. I dare say there were. But no one saw them, and so we do not know anything about them. They did not exist till Art had invented them.&#8221;</p>



<p>As if commenting directly on Monet&#8217;s works, which would not be shown for another five years, Wilde concludes that: &#8220;things are because we see them, and what we see, and how we see it, depends on the Arts that have influenced us. To look at a thing is very different from seeing a thing. One does not see anything until one sees its beauty.&#8221; Monet&#8217;s disassembly of soot-laced fog into a diaphanous fabric (replete with &#8220;all sorts of colours&#8221;, as the artist himself explained; &#8220;there are black, brown, yellow, green, purple fogs&#8221;) would soon supersede the visions of his predecessors and irreversibly alter how London saw itself.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image"><img decoding="async" src="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/images/ic/480xn/p0jyqtm3.jpg.webp" alt="Art Institute of Chicago/Art Resource, NY/Scala, Florence Waterloo Bridge, Grey Weather,1900, oil on canvas (Credit: Art Institute of Chicago/ Art Resource, NY/ Scala, Florence)"/><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Waterloo Bridge, Grey Weather,1900, oil on canvas (Credit: Art Institute of Chicago/ Art Resource, NY/ Scala, Florence)</figcaption></figure>



<p>Set side-by-side comparable views of the Thames by Monet and by his esteemed British forebear, JMW Turner, to whom the Impressionist was occasionally likened, and it is difficult to believe that the two artists set their easels in the same city. Turner&#8217;s 1830-35 painting&nbsp;<a target="_blank" href="https://www.tate.org.uk/art/artworks/turner-the-thames-above-waterloo-bridge-n01992" rel="noreferrer noopener">The Thames Above Waterloo Bridge</a>, which glimpses the city from a similar vantage to Monet&#8217;s Waterloo Bridge, Sunlight Effect, 1900, illustrates the divergence. While both artists are obsessed with light, for Turner the Sun was a muscular god, not a fine hook ripping at the threads holding reality together. In Turner&#8217;s canvas, smoke belching forth from a factory is not a blessing but a scar. The dark billows seem to assume the shape of a yelping black dog, leaping from a chimney, scratching at the sky. The poisonous pollution is an irritation, not a revelation.</p>



<p>To appreciate just how revolutionary Monet&#8217;s vision of London was at the turn of the 20th Century, one need merely compare it with that of his younger self. Thirty years earlier, the fledgling artist, then in his late 20s, took refuge in London, fleeing his hometown of Le Havre to avoid fighting in the Franco-Prussian War. An early painting by Monet that he undertook at the time, The Thames below Westminster, 1871, illustrates the instinctive allure fog held for him and finds the emerging artist gracefully weighing the relative gravities of light and levitations of architecture, as the Houses of Parliament begin to lose themselves in the tightening fabric of fog. But what holds our focus is not the strobing analysis of light&#8217;s essence that we find in his later paintings, such as Charing Cross Bridge, The Thames, 1903, but the rigid armature of the wooden pier we see being constructed clamorously on the right of the canvas. The fog is vivid, not yet vital.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image"><img decoding="async" src="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/images/ic/480xn/p0jyqv7g.jpg.webp" alt="Musée des Beaux-Arts, Lyon, Image Lyon MBA. Photo: Alain Bass Charing Cross Bridge, The Thames, 1903, oil on canvas (Credit: Musée des Beaux-Arts, Lyon, Image Lyon MBA. Photo: Alain Bass)"/><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Charing Cross Bridge, The Thames, 1903, oil on canvas (Credit: Musée des Beaux-Arts, Lyon, Image Lyon MBA. Photo: Alain Bass)</figcaption></figure>



<p>Though we tend to think of Impressionism as a movement devoted to capturing – quickly and at first hand – fleeting moments, Monet&#8217;s London series succeeded in turning this ideology on its head. Far from chronicling transitory glimmers, the Thames paintings are complex compressions of multiple moments artificially fused, reworked continuously over an expanse not of minutes but years. Rather than tending to a single canvas at a time, Monet would strew about his hotel room scores of fragmentary studies – fits-and-starts he would fumble for when a particular cohesion of mist, smoke and sunlight would reappear again. As no given light effect would linger more than a few minutes, every canvas is a palimpsest of echoing atmospherics.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Back in his studio in Giverny, Monet spent four years revising his visions in an effort to coax from their archaeologies of light harmonies that could hold them together like a symphony. The result is an immersive, misunderstood, multi-panel masterpiece that was scattered to the four winds when the paintings were sold off individually to international collectors. The Courtauld&#8217;s exhibition offers a precious opportunity to surround oneself with more than &nbsp;a third of the works that Monet started between 1899 and 1901 – a convergence of wonder that shaped the way we see and, like the miracles of light they capture, may never occur again.&nbsp;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/a-mesmerising-mirage-how-monets-paintings-changed-the-way-we-see-london/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>AI and bots allegedly used to fraudulently boost music streams</title>
		<link>/ai-and-bots-allegedly-used-to-fraudulently-boost-music-streams/</link>
					<comments>/ai-and-bots-allegedly-used-to-fraudulently-boost-music-streams/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[root]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 04 Nov 2024 15:19:03 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Tech]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=17</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[A singer from the United States has been accused of manipulating music streaming platforms using AI technologies and bots to fraudulently inflate his stream statistics and earn millions of dollars in royalties. Michael Smith, 52, from North Carolina, faces charges of wire fraud, conspiracy to commit wire fraud and money laundering. According to the&#160;BBC, authorities...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image"><img decoding="async" src="https://www.artificialintelligence-news.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/AI-and-bots-allegedly-used-to-fraudulently-boost-music-streams-scaled-e1726113060930.jpg" alt="AI and bots allegedly used to fraudulently boost music streams"/></figure>



<h1 class="wp-block-heading has-medium-font-size"></h1>



<p><a href="https://www.facebook.com/sharer/sharer.php?u=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.artificialintelligence-news.com%2Fnews%2Fai-and-bots-allegedly-used-to-fraudulently-boost-music-streams%2F" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank"></a><a href="https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?text=AI%20and%20bots%20allegedly%20used%20to%20fraudulently%20boost%20music%20streams&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.artificialintelligence-news.com%2Fnews%2Fai-and-bots-allegedly-used-to-fraudulently-boost-music-streams%2F" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank"></a><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/sharing/share-offsite/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.artificialintelligence-news.com%2Fnews%2Fai-and-bots-allegedly-used-to-fraudulently-boost-music-streams%2F" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank"></a><a href="http://reddit.com/submit?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.artificialintelligence-news.com%2Fnews%2Fai-and-bots-allegedly-used-to-fraudulently-boost-music-streams%2F&amp;title=AI%20and%20bots%20allegedly%20used%20to%20fraudulently%20boost%20music%20streams" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank"></a><a href="https://www.artificialintelligence-news.com/news/ai-and-bots-allegedly-used-to-fraudulently-boost-music-streams/"></a></p>



<p>A singer from the United States has been accused of manipulating music streaming platforms using AI technologies and bots to fraudulently inflate his stream statistics and earn millions of dollars in royalties.</p>



<p>Michael Smith, 52, from North Carolina, faces charges of wire fraud, conspiracy to commit wire fraud and money laundering.</p>



<p>According to the&nbsp;<em><a href="https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/cly3ld9wy3eo" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">BBC</a></em>, authorities allege that this is the first time AI has been used to allow such a large-scale streaming scam. U.S. Attorney Damian Williams emphasised the scope of the fraud, claiming that Smith took millions of dollars in royalties that should have gone to real musicians, songwriters and rights holders.</p>



<p>The accusations stem from an unsealed indictment alleging that Smith distributed hundreds of thousands of AI-generated songs across multiple streaming platforms. To avoid detection, automated bots streamed the tracks—sometimes up to 10,000 at a time. Smith allegedly earned more than $10 million in illegal royalties over several years.</p>



<p>The FBI played a crucial role in the investigation. The agency’s acting assistant director, Christie M. Curtis, explained that the agency was dedicated to tracking down those who misuse technology to rob people of their earnings while simultaneously undermining the efforts of real artists.</p>



<p>According to the indictment, Smith began working with the CEO of an undisclosed AI music firm around 2018. This co-conspirator allegedly provided Smith with thousands of AI-generated tracks each month. In exchange, Smith offered metadata such as song titles and artist names, and offered a share of streaming earnings.</p>



<p>One email exchange between Smith and the unnamed CEO in March 2019 demonstrates how the plot took shape. The executive stated, “Keep in mind what we’re doing musically here…this is not ‘music,’ [but] ‘instant music’).” The email emphasises the operation’s intentional nature, as well as the use of AI to generate large amounts of content with minimal effort. According to the indictment, the technology improved over time, making it harder for streaming platforms to detect fraudulent streams.</p>



<p>In another email dated February, Smith boasted that his AI-generated tracks had accumulated over 4 billion streams and $12 million in royalties since 2019. If convicted, Smith faces significant prison time for the charges brought against him.</p>



<p>The Smith case is not the only one involving bogus music streaming royalties. Earlier this year, a Danish man received an 18-month term for a similar plan. Music streaming platforms like Spotify, Apple Music and YouTube forbid bots and artificial streams from being used to boost royalties. Such behaviour is disruptive and illegal, and platforms have taken steps to combat it through policy changes. For instance, if artificial streams are detected, Spotify charges the label or distributor and music can earn royalties only if it meets certain criteria.</p>



<p>Nevertheless, the proliferation of AI-generated music continues to disrupt the music industry. Musicians and record companies fear they will lose revenue and recognition due to AI tools capable of creating music, text and images. Such tools reportedly sometimes use content that musicians and other creators have posted on the internet, raising questions about copyright infringement.</p>



<p>Tension came to a head in 2023 when a track that mimicked the voices of popular artists Drake and The Weeknd went viral, prompting streaming platforms to remove it. Earlier this year, several high-profile musicians, including Billie Eilish, Elvis Costello and Aerosmith, signed an open letter urging the music industry to address the “predatory” use of AI to generate content.</p>



<p><em>(Photo by&nbsp;<a href="https://unsplash.com/@othentikisra?utm_content=creditCopyText&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_source=unsplash">israel palacio</a>)</em></p>



<h1 class="wp-block-heading has-medium-font-size">About the Author</h1>



<p class="has-small-font-size"><img decoding="async" src="https://www.artificialintelligence-news.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/muhammadprof2.jpeg" alt="AI and bots allegedly used to fraudulently boost music streams" style="width: 20px;"> <strong>As </strong>a tech journalist, Zul focuses on topics including cloud computing, cybersecurity, and disruptive technology in the enterprise industry. He has expertise in moderating webinars and presenting content on video, in addition to having a background in networking technology.</p>



<p class="has-small-font-size">By&nbsp;<a href="https://www.artificialintelligence-news.com/news/author/muhammadzulhusni/">Muhammad Zulhusni</a>&nbsp;|&nbsp;September 16, 2024</p>



<p class="has-small-font-size">Categories:&nbsp;<a href="https://www.artificialintelligence-news.com/categories/ai-applications/">Applications</a>,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.artificialintelligence-news.com/categories/artificial-intelligence/">Artificial Intelligence</a>,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.artificialintelligence-news.com/categories/ai-industries/">Industries</a>,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.artificialintelligence-news.com/categories/ai-security/">Security</a>,</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/ai-and-bots-allegedly-used-to-fraudulently-boost-music-streams/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Pakistan ranked among top countries in cybersecurity, says IT minister</title>
		<link>/pakistan-ranked-among-top-countries-in-cybersecurity-says-it-minister/</link>
					<comments>/pakistan-ranked-among-top-countries-in-cybersecurity-says-it-minister/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[root]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 04 Nov 2024 15:16:43 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Tech]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=14</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[KARACHI: Minister of State for Information Te­­chnology and Telecom Shaza Fatima Khawaja has disclosed that Pakis­tan has been recognised in the Top Tier-1 (Role-Mod­elling) of the ITU-Global Cybersecurity Index (GCI-V5) 2024, reflecting the country’s strides in strengthening cybersecurity and resilience. Addressing an event titled ‘Digital Pakistan Cybersecurity Hackathon 2024’, officially launched here on Wednesday, she...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>KARACHI: Minister of State for Information Te­­chnology and Telecom Shaza Fatima Khawaja has disclosed that Pakis­tan has been recognised in the Top Tier-1 (Role-Mod­elling) of the ITU-Global Cybersecurity Index (GCI-V5) 2024, reflecting the country’s strides in strengthening cybersecurity and resilience.</p>



<p>Addressing an event titled ‘<a rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank" href="https://cyberhackathon.pk/">Digital Pakistan Cybersecurity Hackathon 2024</a>’, officially launched here on Wednesday, she said that this milestone is a testament to the dedicated efforts made by stakeholders across the government, industry, academia, and law enforcement agencies.</p>



<p>She said the government wanted to make Pakistan a hub of information technology.</p>



<p>Organised by Ignite under the auspices of the Ministry of IT and Telecom, this flagship event marks the beginning of a nationwide series that will see 521 teams from across Pakistan competing in cybersecurity challenges designed to identify, nurture, and promote local talent in this critical field.</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote is-layout-flow wp-block-quote-is-layout-flow">
<p>‘Digital Pakistan Cybersecurity Hackathon 2024’ officially launched</p>
</blockquote>



<p>Ms Khawaja also expressed her gratitude to all participants, partner organisations and organisers who contributed to the success of the Karachi launch.</p>



<p>Events like the Digital Pakis­tan Cybersecurity Hackathon are instrumental in developing an ecosystem of innovation and collaboration in cybersecurity, she said.</p>



<p>Secretary IT and Telecom Zar­­­rar Hasham Khan highlighted the ministry’s commitment to developing national cybersecurity expertise and capabilities.</p>



<p>The Ministry of IT and Telecom remains steadfast in its pursuit of initiatives that support cybersecurity talent development and innovation across the country, Mr Khan said.</p>



<p>Events like the Cybersecurity Hackathon help foster a secure digital environment while providing vital skills and opportunities for young cybersecurity professionals, he said.</p>



<p>“It is through such initiatives that we build not only a skilled workforce but also a resilient digital infrastructure that will serve as the backbone of Pakistan’s digital future.</p>



<p>CEO of Ignite, Adeel Aijaz Shaikh, emphasised the organisation’s role in establishing the Hackathon as a national brand for cybersecurity talent identification and workforce readiness.</p>



<p>The Digital Pakistan Cyber­security Hackathon has become a singular, national platform for cultivating cybersecurity expertise in Pakistan, he said.</p>



<p>“This year, we conducted cybersecurity awareness sessions and practical training workshops in 16 cities, resulting in over 3,000 individuals completing hands-on cybersecurity training. The launch event in Karachi represents our vision to create a future-ready cybersecurity workforce that will defend Pakistan’s digital borders,” Mr Shaikh said.</p>



<p><em>Published in Dawn, October 31st, 2024</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/pakistan-ranked-among-top-countries-in-cybersecurity-says-it-minister/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>‘Pakistan unable to launch bonds’</title>
		<link>/pakistan-unable-to-launch-bonds/</link>
					<comments>/pakistan-unable-to-launch-bonds/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[root]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 04 Nov 2024 15:15:16 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Finance]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=10</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[KARACHI: The government’s inability to launch Euro and Panda bonds could put the economy under stress, which may not help the country get improved ratings from international rating agencies, said financial experts. “The government is yet not able to launch bonds in the international market to raise dollars due to poor country ratings given by...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>KARACHI: The government’s inability to launch Euro and Panda bonds could put the economy under stress, which may not help the country get improved ratings from international rating agencies, said financial experts.</p>



<p>“The government is yet not able to launch bonds in the international market to raise dollars due to poor country ratings given by the international rating agencies,” said sources in the financial sector.</p>



<p>The finance minister and the State Bank of Pakistan governor met top-class rating agencies in Washington last month to convince them that the macroeconomic numbers of the economy have improved. However, a favourable outcome has yet to be noted.</p>



<p>Twoo rating agencies have already upgraded Pakistan’s rating by one notch. On Jul 29, Fitch upgraded Pakistan’s long-term issuer rating by one notch to CCC+, and on Aug 28, Moody’s upgraded Pakistan to Caa2.</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote is-layout-flow wp-block-quote-is-layout-flow">
<p>SBP purchases $1.3bn from open market</p>
</blockquote>



<p>“Despite all efforts and hiring companies for the launching of Panda bonds in the Chinese market, the government has failed to achieve this goal,” said Atif Ahmed, a banker and currency market expert.</p>



<p>Finance Minister Mohammad Auran­gzeb met China’s Vice Minister of Finance Liao Min in Washington last week. The minister reportedly said the government aims to launch an inaugural Panda bond in the Chinese market to diversify its financing base.</p>



<p>Financial experts said the Chinese companies are less interested in buying Pakistani bonds despite possibly higher returns.</p>



<p>The failure to sell Pakistan International Airlines (PIA) reflects that foreign investors are uninterested. Only one domestic real estate developer could qualify, but the bidding ended without a positive conclusion.</p>



<p>Prime Minister Shahbaz Sharif recently visited Saudi Arabia and Qatar and announced that the two countries were ready to invest billions of dollars in diversified sectors. However, there was little enthusiasm in the financial market about the possible investments from the two countries.</p>



<p>“What State Bank can do is to purchase maximum dollars from the local market, restrict imports, keep exchange rate stable for higher selling of export proceeds, curb illegal business of foreign currencies and provide maximum incentives to overseas Pakistanis for more remittances,” said a senior banker and expert on currency movement.</p>



<p><strong>SBP reserves</strong></p>



<p>The State Bank looks to have found an alternative source of dollars as it bought about $1.3bn from the interbank market in June and July.</p>



<p>Despite buying from the market, the foreign exchange reserves of the State Bank fell in July to $9.22bn compared to $9.389bn in June. The State Bank is responsible for external debt servicing, for which the government made efforts to reschedule and rollover debts and get loans from the donor agencies as it succeeded in securing a new $7bn Exten­ded Fund Facility from the IMF and received the first tranche in September.</p>



<p>Financial experts said the State Bank has been buying dollars from the interbank market for years to protect or improve its reserves. However, in June 2023, when the country was about to default, it was decided to increase the reserves.</p>



<p>The SBP’s reserves in June 2023 fell below $4bn. The government has the target to increase the reserves of the SBP to $13bn by the end of FY25.</p>



<p>Experts said the remittances jumped by 39 per cent to $8.8bn in the first quarter, providing sufficient liquidity, while exporters’ selling remained high due to a stable exchange rate. At the same time, the imports are still restricted, which means less spending of dollars and less pressure on the external account.</p>



<p>In the first quarter of the current fiscal year, the foreign direct investment inflows also increased by 48pc.</p>



<p><em>Published in Dawn, November 3rd, 2024</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/pakistan-unable-to-launch-bonds/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>ESSAY: THE WOUND THAT IS PALESTINE</title>
		<link>/essay-the-wound-that-is-palestine/</link>
					<comments>/essay-the-wound-that-is-palestine/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[root]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 04 Nov 2024 15:13:23 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=7</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I thank you, members of English PEN and members of the jury, for honouring me with the PEN Pinter Prize. I would like to begin by announcing the name of this year’s ‘Writer of Courage’, who I have chosen to share this award with.&#160; My greetings to you, Alaa Abd El-Fattah, writer of courage and...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>I thank you, members of English PEN and members of the jury, for honouring me with the PEN Pinter Prize. I would like to begin by announcing the name of this year’s ‘Writer of Courage’, who I have chosen to share this award with.&nbsp;</p>



<p>My greetings to you, Alaa Abd El-Fattah, writer of courage and my fellow awardee. We hoped and prayed that you would be released in September, but the Egyptian government decided that you were too beautiful a writer and too dangerous a thinker to be freed yet. But you are here in this room with us. You are the most important person here. From prison you wrote, “[M]y words lost any power and yet they continued to pour out of me. I still had a voice, even if only a handful would listen.” We are listening, Alaa. Closely.</p>



<p>Greetings to you, too, my beloved Naomi Klein, friend to both Alaa and me. Thank you for being here tonight. It means the world to me.</p>



<p>Greetings to all of you gathered here, as well as to those who are invisible perhaps to this wonderful audience, but as visible to me as anybody else in this room. I am speaking of my friends and comrades in prison in India — lawyers, academics, students, journalists — Umar Khalid, Gulfisha Fatima, Khalid Saifi, Sharjeel Imam, Rona Wilson, Surendra Gadling, Mahesh Raut. I speak to you, my friend Khurram Parvaiz, one of the most remarkable people I know, you’ve been in prison for three years, and to you too Irfan Mehraj, and to the thousands incarcerated in Kashmir and across the country whose lives have been devastated.</p>



<p>When Ruth Borthwick, the chair of English PEN and of the Pinter panel, first wrote to me about this honour, she said the Pinter Prize is awarded to a writer who has sought to define “the&nbsp;real&nbsp;truth of our lives and our societies” through “unflinching, unswerving, fierce intellectual determination.”&nbsp;That is a quote from Harold Pinter’s Nobel Prize acceptance speech.</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote is-layout-flow wp-block-quote-is-layout-flow">
<p>Writer and activist Arundhati Roy has been awarded the PEN Pinter Prize 2024. This is an annual award set up by English PEN in the memory of playwright Harold Pinter. Shortly after having been named for the prize, Roy announced that her share of the prize money will be donated to the Palestinian Children’s Relief Fund. She named Alaa Abd el-Fattah, British-Egyptian writer and activist, a ‘Writer of Courage’ who she would share her award with. The following is her acceptance speech for the prize, delivered on the evening of October 10 at the British Library…</p>
</blockquote>



<p>The word ‘unflinching’ made me pause for a moment, because I think of myself as someone who is almost permanently flinching.</p>



<p>I would like to dwell a little on the theme of ‘flinching’ and ‘unflinching’, which may be best illustrated by Harold Pinter himself:</p>



<p>“I was present at a meeting at the US embassy in London in the late 1980s.</p>



<p>“The United States Congress was about to decide whether to give more money to the Contras in their campaign against the state of Nicaragua. I was a member of a delegation speaking on behalf of Nicaragua, but the most important member of this delegation was a Father John Metcalf. The leader of the US body was Raymond Seitz (then number two to the ambassador, later ambassador himself). Father Metcalf said: ‘Sir, I am in charge of a parish in the north of Nicaragua. My parishioners built a school, a health centre, a cultural centre. We have lived in peace. A few months ago, a Contra force attacked the parish. They destroyed everything: the school, the health centre, the cultural centre. They raped nurses and teachers, slaughtered doctors, in the most brutal manner. They behaved like savages. Please demand that the US government withdraw its support from this shocking terrorist activity.’</p>



<p>“Raymond Seitz had a very good reputation as a rational, responsible and highly sophisticated man. He was greatly respected in diplomatic circles. He listened, paused and then spoke with some gravity. ‘Father,’ he said, ‘let me tell you something. In war, innocent people always suffer.’ There was a frozen silence. We stared at him. He did not flinch.”</p>



<p>Remember that President Reagan called the Contras “the moral equivalent of our Founding Fathers.” A turn of phrase that he was clearly fond of. He also used it to describe the CIA-backed Afghan Mujahideen, who then morphed into the Taliban. And it is the Taliban who rule Afghanistan today, after waging a 20-year-long war against the US invasion and occupation. Before the Contras and the Mujahideen, there was the war in Vietnam and the ‘unflinching’ US military doctrine that ordered its soldiers to “Kill Anything That Moves.”</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote is-layout-flow wp-block-quote-is-layout-flow">
<p>I am expected to equivocate to protect myself, my ‘neutrality’, my intellectual standing. This is the part where I am meant to lapse into moral equivalence and condemn Hamas, the other militant groups in Gaza and their ally Hezbollah, in Lebanon, for killing civilians and taking people hostage. And to condemn the people of Gaza who celebrated the Hamas attack… I refuse to play the condemnation game. Let me make myself clear. I do not tell oppressed people how to resist their oppression or who their allies should be.</p>
</blockquote>



<p>If you read the Pentagon Papers and other documents on US war aims in Vietnam, you can enjoy some lively ‘unflinching’ discussions about how to commit genocide — is it better to kill people outright or to starve them slowly? Which would&nbsp;look&nbsp;better?</p>



<p>The problem that the compassionate mandarins in the Pentagon faced was that, unlike Americans, who, according to them, want “life, happiness, wealth, power”, Asians “stoically accept…the destruction of wealth and the loss of lives” — and force America to carry their “strategic logic to its conclusion, which is genocide.” A terrible burden to be borne ‘unflinchingly’.</p>



<p>And here we are, all these years later, more than a year into yet another genocide. The US and Israel’s&nbsp;unflinching&nbsp;and ongoing televised genocide in Gaza, and now Lebanon, in defence of a colonial occupation and an Apartheid state. The death toll, so far, is officially 42,000, a majority of them women and children. This does not include those who died screaming under the rubble of buildings, neighbourhoods, whole cities, and those whose bodies have not yet been recovered. A recent study by Oxfam says that more children have been killed by Israel in Gaza than in the equivalent period of any other war in the last 20 years.</p>



<p>To assuage their collective guilt for their early years of indifference towards one genocide — the Nazi extermination of millions of European Jews — the United States and Europe have prepared the grounds for another.</p>



<p>Like every state that has carried out ethnic cleansing and genocide in history, Zionists in Israel — who believe themselves to be “the chosen people” — began by dehumanising Palestinians before driving them off their land and murdering them.</p>



<p>[Former Israeli] Prime Minister Menachem Begin called Palestinians “two-legged beasts”, [former Israeli prime minister] Yitzhak Rabin called them “grasshoppers” who “could be crushed” and [former Israeli prime minister] Golda Meir said “There was no such thing as Palestinians.” [Former UK prime minister] Winston Churchill, that famous warrior against fascism, said, “I do not admit that the dog in the manger has the final right to the manger, even though he may have lain there for a very long time”, and then went on to declare that a “higher race” had the final right to the manger.</p>



<p>Once those two-legged beasts, grasshoppers, dogs and non-existent people were murdered, ethnically cleansed and ghettoised, a new country was born. It was celebrated as “a land without people for a people without a land.” The nuclear-armed state of Israel was to serve as a military outpost and gateway to the natural wealth and resources of the Middle East for the US and Europe. A lovely coincidence of aims and objectives.</p>



<p>The new state was supported unhesitatingly and ‘unflinchingly’, armed and bankrolled, coddled and applauded, no matter what crimes it committed. It grew up like a protected child in a wealthy home, whose parents smile proudly as it commits atrocity upon atrocity. No wonder today it feels free to&nbsp;boast&nbsp;openly about committing genocide. (At least The Pentagon Papers were secret. They had to be stolen. And leaked.)</p>



<p>No wonder Israeli soldiers seem to have lost all sense of decency. No wonder they flood social media with depraved videos of themselves wearing the lingerie of women they have killed or displaced, videos of themselves mimicking dying Palestinians and wounded children or raped and tortured prisoners, images of themselves blowing up buildings while they smoke cigarettes or jive to music on their headphones. Who are these people?&nbsp;</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image"><img decoding="async" src="https://i.dawn.com/primary/2024/10/671478a738d94.jpg" alt="Arundhathi Roy accepts the PEN Pinter Prize 2024. She is holding a portrait of Alaa Abd el-Fattah, British-Egyptian writer and activist, named Writer of Courage by her | English PEN"/><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Arundhathi Roy accepts the PEN Pinter Prize 2024. She is holding a portrait of Alaa Abd el-Fattah, British-Egyptian writer and activist, named Writer of Courage by her | English PEN</figcaption></figure>



<p>What can possibly justify what Israel is doing?</p>



<p>The answer, according to Israel and its allies, as well as the Western media, is the Hamas attack on Israel on October 7th&nbsp;last year. The killing of Israeli civilians and the taking of Israeli hostages. According to them, history only began a year ago.</p>



<p>So, this is the part in my speech where I am expected to equivocate to protect myself, my ‘neutrality’, my intellectual standing. This is the part where I am meant to lapse into moral equivalence and condemn Hamas, the other militant groups in Gaza and their ally Hezbollah, in Lebanon, for killing civilians and taking people hostage. And to condemn the people of Gaza who celebrated the Hamas attack. Once that’s done, it all becomes easy, doesn’t it? Ah well. Everybody is terrible, what can one do? Let’s go shopping instead…</p>



<p>I refuse to play the condemnation game. Let me make myself clear. I do not tell oppressed people how to resist their oppression or who their allies should be.</p>



<p>When US President Joe Biden met with [Israeli] Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu and the Israeli war cabinet during a visit to Israel in October 2023, he said, “I don’t believe you have to be a Jew to be a Zionist, and I am a Zionist.”</p>



<p>Unlike President Joe Biden, who calls himself a non-Jewish Zionist and&nbsp;unflinchingly&nbsp;bankrolls and arms Israel while it commits its war crimes, I am not going to declare myself or define myself in any way that is narrower than my writing. I am what I write.</p>



<p>I am acutely aware that, being the writer that I am, the non-Muslim that I am and the woman that I am, it would be very difficult, perhaps impossible for me to survive very long under the rule of Hamas, Hezbollah or the Iranian regime. But that is not the point here. The point is to educate ourselves about the history and the circumstances under which they came to exist.</p>



<p>The point is that, right now, they are fighting against an ongoing genocide. The point is to ask ourselves whether a liberal, secular fighting force can go up against a genocidal war machine. Because, when all the powers of the world are against them, who do they have to turn to but God?</p>



<p>I am aware that Hezbollah and the Iranian regime have vocal detractors in their own countries, some who also languish in jails or have faced far worse outcomes. I am aware that some of their actions — the killing of civilians and the taking of hostages on October 7th&nbsp;by Hamas — constitute war crimes. However, there cannot be an equivalence between this and what Israel and the United States are doing in Gaza, in the West Bank and now in Lebanon. The root of&nbsp;all&nbsp;the violence, including the violence of October 7th, is Israel’s occupation of Palestinian land and its subjugation of the Palestinian people. History did not begin on 7 October, 2023.</p>



<p>I ask you, which of us sitting in this hall would willingly submit to the indignity that Palestinians in Gaza and the West Bank have been subjected to for decades? What peaceful means have the Palestinian people not tried? What compromise have they not accepted — other than the one that requires them to crawl on their knees and eat dirt?&nbsp;</p>



<p>Israel is not fighting a war of self-defence. It is fighting a war of aggression. A war to occupy more territory, to strengthen its Apartheid apparatus and tighten its control on Palestinian people and the region.</p>



<p>Since October 7th,&nbsp;2023, apart from the tens of thousands of people it has killed, Israel has displaced the majority of Gaza’s population, many times over. It has bombed hospitals. It has deliberately targeted and killed doctors, aid workers and journalists. A whole population is being starved — their history is sought to be erased.</p>



<p>All this is supported both morally and materially by the wealthiest, most powerful governments in the world. And their media. (Here I include my country, India, which supplies Israel with weapons, as well as thousands of workers.) There is no daylight between these countries and Israel.</p>



<p>In the last year alone, the US has spent 17.9 billion dollars in military aid to Israel. So, let us, once and for all, dispense with the lie about the US being a mediator, a restraining influence, or as Alexandria Ocasio-Cortez (considered to be on the extreme Left of mainstream US politics) put it, “working tirelessly for a ceasefire.” A party to the genocide cannot be a mediator.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Not all the power and money, not all the weapons and propaganda on earth can any longer hide the wound that is Palestine. The wound through which the whole world, including Israel, bleeds.</p>



<p>Polls show that a majority of the citizens in the countries whose governments enable the Israeli genocide have made it clear that they do not agree with this. We have watched those marches of hundreds of thousands of people — including a young generation of Jews who are tired of being used, tired of being lied to.</p>



<p>Who would have imagined that we would live to see the day when German police would arrest Jewish citizens for protesting against Israel and Zionism and accuse them of anti-Semitism? Who would have thought the US government would, in the service of the Israeli state, undermine its cardinal principle of free speech by banning pro-Palestine slogans? The so-called moral architecture of Western democracies — with a few honourable exceptions — has become a grim laughingstock in the rest of the world.</p>



<p>When Benjamin Netanyahu holds up a map of the Middle East in which Palestine has been erased and Israel stretches from the river to the sea, he is applauded as a visionary, who is working to realise the dream of a Jewish homeland. But when Palestinians and their supporters chant “From the river to the sea, Palestine will be free”, they are accused of explicitly calling for the genocide of Jews.</p>



<p>Are they really? Or is that a sick imagination, projecting its own darkness on to others? An imagination that cannot countenance diversity, cannot countenance the idea of living in a country alongside other people, equally, with equal rights. Like everybody else in the world does. An imagination that cannot afford to acknowledge that Palestinians want to be free, like South Africa is, like India is, like all countries that have thrown off the yoke of colonialism are. Countries that are diverse, deeply, maybe even fatally, flawed, but free.</p>



<p>When South Africans were chanting their popular rallying cry, “Amandla!” [Power to the people], were they calling for the genocide of white people? They were not. They were calling for the dismantling of the Apartheid state. Just as the Palestinians are.</p>



<p>The war that has now begun will be terrible. But it will eventually dismantle Israeli Apartheid. The whole world will be far safer for everyone — including for Jewish people — and far more just. It will be like pulling an arrow from our wounded heart.</p>



<p>If the US government withdrew its support of Israel, the war could stop today. Hostilities could end right this minute. Israeli hostages could be freed, Palestinian prisoners could be released. The negotiations with Hamas and the other Palestinian stakeholders, that must inevitably follow the war, could instead take place now and prevent the suffering of millions of people. How sad that most people would consider this a naïve, laughable proposition.&nbsp;</p>



<p>As I conclude, let me turn to your words, Alaa Abd El-Fatah, from your book of prison writing,&nbsp;You Have Not Yet Been Defeated. I have rarely read such beautiful words about the meaning of victory and defeat — and the political necessity of honestly looking despair in the eye. I have rarely seen writing in which a citizen separates himself from the state, from the generals and even from the slogans of the square, with such bell-like clarity.</p>



<p>“The centre is treason because there’s room in it only for the General… The centre is treason and I have never been a traitor. They think they’ve pushed us back into the margins. They don’t realise that we never left it, we just got lost for a brief while. Neither the ballot boxes, nor the palaces or the ministries or the prisons or even the graves, are big enough for our dreams. We never sought the centre, because it has no room except for those who abandon the dream. Even the square was not big enough for us, so most of the battles of the revolution happened outside it, and most of the heroes remained outside the frame.”</p>



<p>As the horror we are witnessing in Gaza, and now Lebanon, quickly escalates into a regional war, its real heroes remain outside the frame. But they fight on because they know that one day — From the river to the sea Palestine will be Free.<br>It will.</p>



<p>Keep your eye on your calendar. Not on your clock.</p>



<p>That’s how the people – not the generals – the&nbsp;people&nbsp;fighting for their liberation measure time.</p>



<p><em>The writer is a Booker Prize-winning author and has written about human rights issues in India as well as war and capitalism globally</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/essay-the-wound-that-is-palestine/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
